#### DATA SCIENTIST

Professional Summary

Highly driven Data scientist with 5 years of experience, who brings formidable solutions to diverse complex business problems using machine learning, data mining and statistical analysis.

Familiar with gathering, cleaning and organizing data for use by technical and non-technical personnel. Advanced understanding of statistical, algebraic and other analytical techniques.

Organized, motivated and diligent with significant background in Python, Machine Learning, Deep learning. Experienced working with vast data sets to break down information, gather relevant points and solve advanced business problems. Skilled in predictive modeling, data mining and hypothetical testing.

### Skills

- Machine learning, Statistical Analysis, Data Mining
- · Python, R, SQL.
- · Keras, NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, NLTK, Spacy, TensorFlow.
- Development Tools: Anaconda, PyCharm, Spyder, Visual Studio, RStudio.
- Theoretical Competencies: AGILE, Scrum, Algorithms, Data Structures, Databases, SDLC.
- Version Control: Git, Bitbucket, Perforce.
- Web Technologies: AWS, GCP, Azure.

Work History
Data Scientist 06/2019 to 12/2020
Lockheed Martin Corporation, Durham, NC

### 1.)MedConnect (Jul '20 - Dec '20)

- Developed and implemented a Forecasting algorithm, to predict sales, trx (total count) and nrx (individual count of medicine purchased). Created data visualization graphics, translating complex data sets into comprehensive visual representations.
- Forecasted sales and improved accuracy (MAPE and RMSE) by 30% by implementing advanced forecasting algorithms that were effective in detecting seasonality and trends in the patterns.
- Increased accuracy helped business plan better with respect to budgeting and sales and operations planning. Tuned model parameters (p, d, q for ARIMA) using walk forward validation techniques for optimal model performance.

# 2.) Imperial Bank (Nov '19 - Jul '20)

- Clustered the customers owning the credit cards to optimize the targeting and offerings to increase the customer satisfaction and which in turn enhances revenue.
- Provided Comprehensive analysis and recommended solutions by applying advanced analytical methods to assess factors impacting growth
  and profitability across product and service offering by running the model against unstructured data(Chat Conversations) and identified the
  topic of chat.
- Generated word frequency for 1-gram, 2-gram and 3-gram words and used regex to identify the frequency of the main topics/issues.
   Performed clustering on the TF-IDF to segment the data.

# 3.) Market Place Intelligence (Jun '19 - Nov '19)

- Collaborated with senior personnel to define and meet data modeling standards for deep dive projects.
- Translated benefits of machine learning technology for non-technical audiences, including cost/benefit analyses.
- Evaluated processes and data, identifying productivity gains and sales growth within digitization segment.

Data Scientist 11/2015 to 06/2019 Lockheed Martin Corporation , El Segundo , CA

## 1.) Client: Samsung (Apr '17 - Jun '19)

- Developed voice enabled features for Samsung Health, Internet, and Gallery applications. Performed NLP tasks and techniques such as
  parsing, text pre-processing, named entity recognition, Modelling and Testing. Train set preparation: model building for CNN based Intent
  classifier and Slot tagger.
- Applied statistical and algebraic techniques to interpret key points from gathered data. Best epoch selection by plotting cost functions.
- Coached, developed and motivated team members, providing coaching and mentoring to junior data scientists on SAS and data mining techniques.

Software Engineer 11/2015 to 04/2017 Cgi Group Inc. , Norfolk , VA

- Adjusted design parameters to boost performance and incorporate new features.
- Checked client code for bugs and weaknesses and fixed the issues accordingly.
- Collaborated with business unit team members to design new applications system to enhance client requirements for mobile computing

#### capabilities.

Education

Master of Science::Computer Science, 01/2021 University Of Alabama At Birmingham - City, State

Bachelor of Science: Electronics And Communication Engineering, 07/2015

SVPCET - City

• Graduated with 3.2/4 GPA

Board of Intermediate Education :: Mathematics, Physics And Chemistry , 06/2011 Board Of Intermediate - City

• Graduated with 92.6/100% percentage

High School Diploma::05/2009

Infant Jesus English Medium School - City

• Completed with 88.8/100 percentage.

# Accomplishments

- · Received Best Employee of the month Award from Deloitte for Documenting and Resolving issues which led to a optimal solution to client
- Received APPRECIATION Award from client (SAMSUNG) for colloborating with team in the development of Bixby Project.
- Received PAT on the BACK Award from Tech Mahindra for on time quality delivery work.

#### Certifications

- Completed the certification of "Neural Networks and Deep Learningâ€, "Improving Deep Neural Networksâ€: Hyperparameter tuning, Regularization and Optimization, "Convolutional Neural Networks†in Coursera by Andrew N.G.
- Completed the certification of "Machine Learning†in Coursera by Carlos and Emily.
- Completed the certification of Google Cloud Platform Big Data and Machine Learning Fundamentals in coursera.

### Independent Project

- Text processing using Cognitive Extraction (CogX) Tool: Created Domain Objects and ingested the files for document processing.

  Processed End-to-end document and extracted the entities from the document using different techniques of Explored AWS Textract.
- Topic modelling Using LDA2vec: Implemented a Deep Learning Algorithm, Lda2vec For Categorizing the BBC News dataset topic wise and visualize the top topics the machine has learnt from the dataset provided.